Guide to the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers
The Lewis Walpole Library
- Writings, 1915–1980; Series III; 18.56; 38 boxes
  - Speeches and Lectures
    - University of Delaware, 1961 June 11 (Box 246, Folder 4)
      Remarks for honorary degree award; published as "At Home in an Earlier Age," in University of Melbourne Gazette 28, no. 6 (December 1972).
    - University of Hartford, 1971 October 3 (Box 246, Folder 5-6)
      Remarks at Mortensen Library dedication.
    - University of Melbourne
      - Public lecture, 1947 March 24 (Box 246, Folder 7)
        "Horace Walpole's Library."
      - Commencement address, 1972 August (Box 246, Folder 8)
        Published as "At Home in an Earlier Age," in University of Melbourne Gazette 28, no. 6 (December 1972); same address given in 1961 at University of Delaware.
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1973 November 16 (Box 246, Folder 9)
      Friends of the Library lecture.
    - University of San Francisco, Gleeson Library Associates, 1969 March 9 (Box 246, Folder 10)
      Remarks on award of Sir Thomas More Award for Book Collecting
    - University of Toronto, 1978 November 3 (Box 246, Folder 11)
      Paper given at Conference on Editorial Problems; published as "Editing Familiar Letters" in Editing Correspondence, J. A. Dainard, ed. (New York: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1979).
    - University of Virginia Library, 1969 October 24 (Box 246, Folder 12)
      Remarks at first meeting of the library associates.
    - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1972 January 11 (Box 246, Folder 13)
      Remarks at "An Evening with Wilmarth Lewis."
    - Walpole Society (U.S.)
      - "Horace Walpole Collector", 1932 May (Box 247, Folder 1)
        Paper read at meeting at the University Club, New York.
      - Notes on after-dinner remarks at Farmington, 1967 October 6 (Box 247, Folder 2)
    - Wedgwood International Seminar, 1958 April 18 (Box 247, Folder 3)
    - Wesleyan University, 1967 May 8 (Box 247, Folder 4)
      Paper on editing letters.
    - Westminster School (Simsbury, Ct.), 1940 June 12 (Box 247, Folder 5)
      Commencement address; same address given at Hotchkiss School on June 24, 1940.
    - Women's National Book Association, 1966 October 11 (Box 247, Folder 6)
      Remarks on Blanche Knopf.
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1953 October 1 (Box 247, Folder 7-8)
      Address on the presentation of the Woodrow Wilson Award to Dean Acheson
    - Yale Club of Hartford
      - Annual meeting remarks, 1972 May 24 (Box 247, Folder 9)
      - Remarks at Nathan Hale Award Dinner, 1972 October 11 (Box 247, Folder 10)
    - Yale University
      - Francis Bergen Foundation lecture, 1937 October 6 (Box 247, Folder 11)
      - Remarks to Yale Library Associates, 1938 February 22 (Box 247, Folder 12)
      - Remarks at freshmen Christmas party held in Commons, 1939 December 18 (Box 247, Folder 13)
      - Remarks at a meeting of the Torch Honor Society, circa 1947 (Box 247, Folder 14)
      - Unidentified audience at Yale University Library, 1948 September 16 (Box 247, Folder 15)
        "The Young Waterman"
      - Daniel S. Lamont Memorial Lecture, 1949 February 14 (Box 247, Folder 16)
      - Remarks at 250th Anniversary dinner, 1951 October 19 (Box 247, Folder 17)
      - Interview on "Yale Reports" radio program, 1956 January 8 (Box 247, Folder 18)
        Program broadcast over WTIC, Hartford.
      - Remarks at Yale Arts Festival, 1956 April 20 (Box 247, Folder 19)
        Delivered at the opening of the Yale Arts Festival Exhibit, Art Institute of Chicago.
      - Remarks at University Council anniversary dinner, 1958 February 21 (Box 248, Folder 1)
      - Remarks at dinner for Alfred Whitney Griswold, 1960 February 12 (Box 248, Folder 2)
      - Daniel S. Lamont Memorial Lecture, 1960 April 19 (Box 248, Folder 3, Box 333 (Oversize), Folder 10)
        "Horace Walpole"; also present is the poster advertising the lecture.
      - Remarks at commencement luncheon, 1963 (Box 248, Folder 4)
      - Remarks at inauguration of Kingman Brewster, 1964 April 10 (Box 248, Folder 5-6)
      - Remarks at "Yale in Farmington" dinner, 1966 November 22 (Box 248, Folder 7)
        Dinner held for twelve guests, primarily Yale administrators, featuring printed keepsake.
      - Remarks at dinner for Edwin Foster Blair, 1970 May 8 (Box 248, Folder 8)
      - Interview with Stanley Flinck, 1975–1979 (Box 248, Folder 9)
        Notes for video made by Yale's Office of Public Information and Alumni Communications. The video transcript was published as "A Visit to Farmington" in the Walpole Society Notebook (1979); page proofs are filed here.
    - Yale University, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
      - Remarks at opening of library building, 1963 October 11 (Box 248, Folder 10)
      - Remarks at opening of Cornelius Vanderbilt Collection exhibition, 1968 October 21 (Box 248, Folder 11-12)
        Published as "The Cornelius Vanderbilt Collection" in Yale University Library Gazette 43, no. 3 (January 1969).
    - Yale University. Branford College, 1958 May 7 (Box 249, Folder 1)
      Remarks at senior class banquet
    - Yale University. Calhoun College, 1968 February 5 (Box 249, Folder 2)
      Remarks at college dinner; folder contains letters from Arnold Whitridge and others in 1932-1933 regarding the college's china and bookplate
    - Yale University Law School, 1973 October 19 (Box 249, Folder 3)
      "Woodward Lecture"
    - Yale University Press, 1955 January 7 (Box 249, Folder 4)
      Remarks at Carl Purington Rollins dinner.
    - Yale University. Stiles and Morse colleges, 1962 December 7 (Box 249, Folder 5)
      Remarks at dedication of the new colleges.
    - Yale University Art Gallery
      - Remarks at opening of John Hill Morgan Collection exhibition, 1946 February 22 (Box 249, Folder 6)
      - Remarks on laying of cornerstone, 1952 November 7 (Box 249, Folder 7)
      - Conference on British Art, 1965 (Box 249, Folder 17)
        Lewis participated in, but did not speak at, at this international conference held at the Art Gallery on April 21-23, 1965. On April 23, at the conclusion of the conference, Lewis hosted a dinner for more than fifty of the delegates at his home in Farmington.
      - Lecture to the associates, 1970 February 3 (Box 249, Folder 8)
        First chapter of See for Yourself
    - Other events and unidentified venues
      - "Age of Johnson", 1925 May (Box 249, Folder 9)
      - "The Amateur Book Collector", 1925? (Box 249, Folder 10)
        "Written in '25 or '26 for a ladies club in Htfd"
      - Auchincloss family dinner remarks, 1956 September 18 (Box 249, Folder 11)
      - Dodsley's Collection, 1950 December 4 (Box 249, Folder 12)
        Remarks before a group of eighteenth-century scholars, self-named after Robert Dodsley's A Collection of Poems by Several Hands, who met semi-annually for dinner.
      - "Doubting Thomas", 1956? (Box 249, Folder 13)
      - "Editing Familiar Letters", 1949 March (Box 249, Folder 14)
        Inscribed at top by Lewis: "Where was this read?"
      - "Horace Walpole's Iconography", 1965–1967 (Box 249, Folder 15)
        Notes on remarks made at various dinners.
      - "Rescuing Horace Walpole", undated (Box 249, Folder 16)
      - Memorials and eulogies
        - On Jane Canfield, 1966 April 29 (Box 250, Folder 1)
        - On Fanny Hanna Moore, 1965 December 14 (Box 250, Folder 2)
        - On Nathalie Henderson Swan, 1965 June 2 (Box 250, Folder 3)
        - On Thornton Niven Wilder, 1976 January 18 (Box 250, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous Speeches, 1932–1975 (Box 250, Folder 5)
        Outlines, notes, and sketches from more than thirty speeches Lewis gave at schools, clubs, dinners, and other events; none have substantive texts, though all were captioned and dated by him, and filed in a folder titled "Miscellaneous Speeches."
  - Notebooks
    With the exception of the first volume ("H.W."), all the notebooks had been transferred to Manuscripts and Archives at Sterling Memorial Library in 1979, and were returned to Lewis Walpole Library in 2011. They were accompanied by an envelope (now in Box 251, folder 2) inscribed by Lewis: "Not to be opened until after my death. / Wilmarth S Lewis." The envelope was over inscribed: "Found unsealed in WSL's desk drawer (with the notebooks) by D.B. Engley & Ruth Day while cleaning out his desk. 11/13/79."
    The envelope held a card inscribed by Lewis: "14 Dec. 36 / These note-books are to be sealed without examination & are not to be opened until 14 Nov. 1995. They are to be given to Yale University for the benefit of the Institute of Human Relations, the directors of which at this time of this examination may decide what is to be done with them. / Wilmarth S. Lewis."
    Filed here are notebooks Lewis filled with autograph writings meant for various purposes including research, draft texts and stories, and recording daily activities and thoughts, but they are not comprehensive on any score. Some functioned like commonplace books and contain clippings and quotations from works by other authors; some are written in from both ends to the middle (so were flipped to create a second opening page).
    Titles in the folder list were taken from the covers of the volumes. Span dates were determined from the contents when possible.
    - "H.W." and "G.S.", undated (Box 251, Folder 1)
      Lined commercial notebooks with notes on Horace Walpole.
    - "I 1926" (Box 251, Folder 2)
    - "II - 1926-27 / The Dream", 1926–1927 (Box 251, Folder 3)
    - "III", 1927 (Box 251, Folder 4)
    - "WSL 1929" and "March 1929", 1929–1930 (Box 251, Folder 5)
      Two small notebooks in one folder.
    - "W.S.L. Oct. 14 '30" and "WSL", 1930–1955 (Box 251, Folder 6)
      One small and one large notebook with blue paper covers. The large notebook contains Lewis's poem "The Conning Tower: Any Yum-Yum to Any Marco On the Fifth Anniversary of Their Wedding" both in typescript carbon and clipped from the New York Herald Tribune (February 26, 1935).
    - "WSL 24 Ap 1945", 1945–1957 (Box 251, Folder 7)
      Also written on cover: "Layman Libraries / HW / 1945 / 1957. Mellon."
    - "WSL 1953-1962" (Box 251, Folder 8)
    - "One Man's Education I. 1960-4", 1960–1964 (Box 251, Folder 9)
      Also inscribed on cover: "Shakespeare / The Amateur Reader."
    - "Europe April 10-May 7, 1961", 1961–1964 (Box 251, Folder 10)
      Also inscribed on cover: "Induction Talk 21 Oct 63-11 Ap 64."
    - "OME II / 64-67", 1964–1967 (Box 252, Folder 1)
    - "OME III / 1966-67", 1966–1967 (Box 252, Folder 2)
    - "WSL / 1967-8-9-70", 1967–1970 (Box 252, Folder 3)
    - "WSL / 1970-71-72-73", 1970–1973 (Box 252, Folder 4)
    - "1974-75-76-77-78", 1974–1978 (Box 252, Folder 5)
    - "1979" (Box 252, Folder 6)
    - Subject index to volumes, undated (Box 253, Folder 1)
      A card file created by Lewis to accompany his notebooks.
  - Other Writings
    The subseries includes essays, short stories, and miscellaneous writings both unpublished (in autograph manuscript, typescript, and typescript carbon) and published (journal issues and offprints). The works date from Lewis's undergraduate years through his death, including essays published posthumously.
    Arranged alphabetically by title or genre.
    - "The Art of Editing Letters", undated (Box 254, Folder 1)
      Typescript, corrected.
    - "The Beggar's Opera" by Hogarth and Blake (Cambridge and New Haven: Harvard University Press and Yale University Press, 1965), 1963–1966 (Box 254, Folder 2-7)
      Portfolio consisting of eleven plates, and a brochure written by Lewis and Philip Hofer.
    - Book reviews, 1921, undated (Box 254, Folder 8)
      Group of typescripts and carbons, corrected, with published reviews clipped from the Yale Daily News.
    - "The Boys and Girls of '95", circa 1930 (Box 254, Folder 9)
      Typescript, corrected, of an essay reflecting on the times, from the perspective of age 35.
    - "Building as Seen by a Layman Who has Just Undergone It", circa 1930 (Box 254, Folder 10)
      Typescript, corrected, of an essay about adding onto a house.
    - "The Changing Alumni", 1953 (Box 254, Folder 11)
      An essay for the Yale Daily News.
    - On Chauncey Brewster Tinker, 1946 October 19 (Box 254, Folder 12)
      Typescripts of citation for his Yale honorary degree, with printed copy of the convocation program.
    - "Class Reunion", circa 1947 (Box 254, Folder 13)
      Typescript, corrected, beginning with reflections on turning fifty years of age.
    - "The Collector as Editor", 1949 March (Box 254, Folder 14)
    - "Cushioned Campaigns", circa 1920 (Box 254, Folder 15)
      Typescript, corrected, and manuscript draft pages, of sections of a military memoir (perhaps autobiographical?).
    - "Darkness Visible", 1947–1948 (Box 254, Folder 16)
      An essay about Lewis's eye problem
    - "Editing Horace Walpole's Correspondence", undated (Box 255, Folder 1)
      Typescript, corrected, written for The Yale Review.
    - "Edmund Malone, Horace Walpole, and Shakespeare", 1979 (Box 255, Folder 2)
      Offprint from Evidence in Literary Scholarship: Essays in Memory of James Marshall Osborn (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1979).
    - "Geoffrey in Walpoleshire", circa 1977 (Box 255, Folder 3)
      Offprint from The Book Collector 26, no. 1 (Spring 1977)
    - "Goneril's Husband", 1929 (Box 255, Folder 4)
      Published in Read as You Please (Cleveland: The Rowfant Club, 1977)
    - "The Genesis of Strawberry Hill", 1934 (Box 333 (Oversize), Folder 11-12)
      Published in Metropolitan Museum Studies 5, pt. 1 (1934): 57-92; present here are photographs of images for plates used and not used.
    - "Horace Walpole, Antiquary", 1956 (Box 255, Folder 5)
      Offprint from Essays Presented to Sir Lewis Namier (London: Macmillan, 1956)
    - "Horace Walpole Reread", 1945 (Box 255, Folder 6)
      Tear sheet from Atlantic Monthly 176 (July 1945).
    - "The Last Word", 1949 (Box 255, Folder 7)
      Issue and offprint from The New Colophon 2, part 6 (June 1949).
    - "Let Us Stare at the Wounded", circa 1920 (Box 255, Folder 8)
      Typescript carbon essay.
    - "The Lewis Walpole Library in Farmington", undated (Box 255, Folder 9)
      Typescripts for a booklet (unpublished?) describing the library.
    - "Libraries, Books", circa 1930 (Box 255, Folder 10)
      Typescript draft, annotated, of a guide to the Yale University Library written during the tenure of Andrew Keogh as university librarian (1916-1938). "Libraries, Books" was the title of the original file folder.
    - "A Library Dedicated to the Life and Works of Horace Walpole", 1930 (Box 333 (Oversize), Folder 13-15)
      Published in The Colophon, pt. 3, [no. 4] (September 1930); present here are two printed plates: "Strawberry Hill. The Hall" and "Strawberry Hill. The South Front" with three sets of progressive proofs of the plate "Strawberry Hill. The Hall."
    - "A London Letter", 1924 March 20 (Box 255, Folder 13)
      Autograph manuscript on Brooks's stationery; Lewis later inscribed at the top: "A sample letter for the Tribune (Rejected by Julian Mason)."
    - "Man's Fortune", undated (Box 255, Folder 11-12)
      Typescript, corrected, of an unpublished novel.
    - "Miscellaneous Antiquities" Series
      "Miscellaneous Antiquities" was a series of fourteen small publications written or edited by Lewis between 1927 and 1940, in the spirit of (and meant to continue) the two "Miscellaneous Antiquities" issued by Horace Walpole at Strawberry Hill in 1772; in Lewis's case, they were produced and sent as a year-end gift to friends, family, colleagues, and libraries. While most were privately printed and distributed for Lewis by Edmund B. Thompson at his Hawthorn House press in Windham, Connecticut, a few were published in conjunction with the Grolier Club, Oxford University Press, and Yale University Press.
      Some of the files include typescripts, proof sheets, unbound signatures, and correspondence with printers; see also Edmund B. Thompson's file in Series I (Box 133, folder 14). Lewis's mailing lists are filed with the reader responses in Series I, Boxes 165-166.
      - 6. The Forlorn Printer: Being Notes on Horace Walpole's Alleged Neglect of Thomas Kirgate, 1931–1932 (Box 256, Folder 1)
      - 8. Horace Walpole's Letters from Madame de Sévigné, 1933–1934 (Box 256, Folder 2)
      - 9. Some Short Observations for the Lady Mary Stanhope Concerning the Writing of Ordinary Letters, by Philip, Second Earl of Chesterfield., 1934–1935 (Box 256, Folder 3)
      - 10. Le Triomphe de l'Amitié, ou, l'Histoire de Jacqueline et de Jeanneton, 1935–1936 (Box 256, Folder 4)
      - 12. Bentley's Designs for Walpole's Fugitive Pieces, 1936–1937 (Box 256, Folder 5)
      - 13. Memoranda Walpoliana, 1937–1938 (Box 256, Folder 6)
      - 15. The Impenetrable Secret, probably Invented by Horace Walpole. An Explanation of the Secret., 1939–1940 (Box 256, Folder 7)
      - 16. Notes by Horace Walpole on Several Characters of Shakespeare, 1940–1941 (Box 256, Folder 8)
    - "Mrs. Jones and Son", 1924 (Box 256, Folder 9)
      Typescript, corrected, of an unpublished novel; accompanied by a rejection note from Blanche Knopf.
    - New York Times editorial, 1941 (Box 256, Folder 10)
      Published May 3, 1941, as letter to the editor; folder also contains responses from readers and friends.
    - "Pop Goes the Meistersinger", 1947 (Box 256, Folder 11)
      Typescript and carbon of an essay; accompanied by rejection letter from The New Yorker.
    - "The Portraits of Horace Walpole", 1929–1970 (Box 257, Folder 1-5)
      Co-authored with C. Kingsley Adams, and published in The Volume of the Walpole Society 42 (1968-1970): 1-34. Lewis's research for the project known as "The Iconography of Horace Walpole" began in the 1950s; the files hold his correspondence, worksheets, notes, drafts, and illustration page proofs. Also present is Lewis's correspondence with Cyril Cook regarding English enamels, including Walpole's kingfisher plaque. For further correspondence on the project, see the Adams-Lewis folder in Series I, Box 2, folders 4-6.
    - Short stories
      - "Betty Went By", circa 1925 (Box 257, Folder 6)
        Typescript, corrected, in a folder from the New York literary agents Brandt & Kirkpatrick.
      - "Blank Pages", 1928? (Box 257, Folder 7)
      - "The Connoisseur", 1926 (Box 257, Folder 8)
        Typescript, corrected; accompanied by a rejection letter from Harper & Brothers
      - "Ella", undated (Box 257, Folder 9)
      - "Falling Star", 1929? (Box 257, Folder 10)
      - "Getting Settled", undated (Box 257, Folder 11)
      - "A Jig-saw Puzzle", 1932 (Box 257, Folder 12)
        Typescript, corrected, of a short story; accompanied by a rejection letter from Charles Scribner's Sons.
      - "The Midnight Sleeper to Paddington", 1926 (Box 257, Folder 13)
        Typescript, corrected, with note: "Submitted to Punch '26..."
      - "Mr. Gasebee and the Bomb", 1937 (Box 257, Folder 14)
      - "Young Instructor", 1932 (Box 257, Folder 15)
        Accompanied by a letter from K. S. Crichton of Charles Scribner's Sons
      - Untitled story, circa 1919 (Box 257, Folder 16)
        Typescript, corrected, of a story set in Southern California.
    - "1625 Central Avenue", 1942 (Box 257, Folder 17)
      An autobiographical essay
    - "The Special Convocation", 1946 (Box 257, Folder 18)
      Typescript, corrected, with tear sheets from Yale Alumni Magazine (October 1946).
    - "The Tadpole", 1931 (Box 258, Folder 1-2)
      A play by Lewis and his friend and Farmington neighbor Winchell Smith (1871-1933); accompanied by a dramatic contract; a theater program and daily box office statements from productions at Brandt's Boulevard Theatre in Queens, New York (November-December 1931); daily box office statements from Parsons' Theater in Hartford (December 1931); with two undated newspaper clippings.
    - "Thornton Wilder", 1947 (Box 258, Folder 3)
      Essay commissioned for '47 the Magazine of the Year, but never published.
    - Thoughts on architects and theatre, 1929, 1932 (Box 258, Folder 12)
      Articles published in the Hartford Times and an unidentified New York newspaper.
    - Undergraduate sketches, 1915–1918 (Box 258, Folder 4)
      A group of short sketches in autograph manuscript and typescript, found together in an envelope Lewis had inscribed: "W S L Undergraduate sketches etc."
    - Unidentified work on Horace Walpole, circa 1940 (Box 258, Folder 5-6)
      Typescripts, corrected. Chapters present are titled: Horace Walpole and Strawberry Hill; II. Lady Walpole; III. Eton and Cambridge; IV. The Grand Tour; VI. The Perpetual Friend of London; VII. Strawberry; VIII. The Memoirs are Begun; IX. Fugitive Pieces; X. Officina Arbuteana.
    - Unidentified text fragments, circa 1918 (Box 258, Folder 7)
      Written on Hotel del Coronado and Young Men's Christian Association letterhead.
    - Unidentified text fragments, undated (Box 258, Folder 8)
    - Verses, 1935–1966 (Box 258, Folder 9)
      Poems by Lewis in typescript, with one published in (and clipped from) Franklin P. Adams's column "The Conning Tower"; the latter, titled "Any Yum-Yum to Any Marco" and signed "Lefty," was written "On the Fifth Anniversary of Their Wedding" and published in the New York Herald Tribune on February 26, 1935.
    - "But--is God a Yale Man?" quote, 1950–1965 (Box 258, Folder 10)
      Cites from various sources of Lewis's statement related to choosing a new president for Yale University. Lewis's original essay is not present here.
    - Bibliography of Wilmarth S. Lewis, 1979 (Box 258, Folder 11)
      A chronologically arranged bibliography compiled by Lewis's librarian Catherine Jestin.
- Personal Papers, 1800–1980; Series IV; 21.94; 27 boxes + 1 broadside
  Series IV is organized into eight subseries: Academic Awards, Honors, and Associations; Address Books; Appointment Calendars; Family Papers; Legal Files; Scrapbooks and Clippings; Travel Files; and Other Papers.
  The series holds a variety of material documenting Lewis's public and private lives, ranging from his eleven honorary degrees very publicly awarded by ten universities and the nine scrapbooks and twenty-four folders of clippings that cover those and other events, to his 1896 baptism certificate and World War II gasoline ration book. The Family Papers are primarily material collected by his brother Charles and forwarded to Farmington when his life was drawing to a close; included is Charles's genealogical research and some nineteenth-century family documents, as well as Wilmarth Lewis's copies of legal papers from family members' estates. Legal Files hold papers from the estate of Annie Burr Lewis and her mother Emma Brewster Auchincloss, the latter as it related to his inheritances. Travel Files contain material from several international trips, including two to Australia, that Lewis made between 1947 and 1972; the folders for the United States hold only transportation receipts and records for his travels from Farmington to Newport and New York, and some flights to California. The last subseries, Other Papers, contains Lewis's school and military papers, and miscellaneous documents such as passports, bibliographic notes, calling cards, bookplates, and, filed at the end, a collection of papers related to his death: obituaries, the memorial booklet from his service, and ephemera from public memorial services held in Farmington, New Haven, and London.
  - Academic Awards, Honors, and Associations
    - Diplomas
      - Thacher School, 1914 (Box 337 (Oversize), Folder 1)
      - Yale University, 1918 (Box 336 (Oversize), Folder 5)
    - Honorary degrees